Software Engineering Radio episode 31,
Agile Documentation.
Welcome everybody to Software
Engineering Radio. Before we actually
start with today's program, which is
about documenting software, um I would
like to address once again the topic of
sound quality. Um as I mentioned before,
um apart from learning and and and
establishing best practices, some of the
problems regarding sound quality can be
fixed with better equipment.
In order to help us um get better
equipment, we actually added a donate
button to our website. So, if you want
to support Software Engineering Radio
financially, then you can do this now
through donations through PayPal.
Now, there's one thing that's important
to me. Software Engineering Radio will
stay free and we are not planning on
having any sponsors or advertising as of
this time. And also, we promise that all
the money you will donate will be used
for buying better audio equipment to get
better sound quality. So, um if you want
to support Software Engineering Radio,
you can actually help us by donating
money to the team through the PayPal
donate button
uh on se-radio.net.
Okay, um
that's that. Uh let's now go on to the
regular program of this episode. In this
episode, we're talking about the
documentation, more specifically about
Agile documentation. Now, um probably
you might think documentation, I'm not
interested in that stuff because I
prefer to write code.
Um
that's probably one of the main problems
in software projects. Um so,
documentation is always considered as an
afterthought if at all. So,
documentation is bad. It looks awful.
People don't know how to lay out it.
People don't know what to document, how
to document, when to document. And in
this episode, we are trying to clarify
some of these things. In order to do
that, we have a guest, Andreas Rüping.
He is the author of a book called Agile
Documentation published by Wiley. You'll
find details in the show notes. And um
So, Andreas, to get started, why don't
you
tell us a little bit a little bit about
yourself and also about the
Agile Documentation thing?
Hello, Markus. Thanks for the
invitation. Hello to all listeners.
Um well, I'm an independent software
architect and software engineer based in
Hamburg.
Um I'm working on various IT projects.
Um I've been in the business for quite a
while.
Uh I'm mostly focusing on on
internet-based architectures these days,
web applications, content management.
Um and
the
documentation issue is something I've
been looking at for a couple of years
now
um because it comes up in virtually
every project. Um
It regardless of what technology you
use.
And I've been observing some best
practices of what works well in
documentation and what doesn't seem to
work well.
And eventually I started to shape these
experiences and these best practices
into patterns. And that is how um this
book evolved. It's called Agile
Documentation, as you said. And the
title comes from the fact that I've
been
impressed with some of what the Agile
methods say about documentation, namely
that too much documentation can actually
do more harm than good.
And um so, I felt that we can learn a
lot from Agile
from the Agile methods about uh what
good documentation is and what good
documentation isn't.
I think one important thing to learn
from Agile methods is that documentation
and understanding is not the same thing.
You can document many things, but that
doesn't mean you have documented
everything that the team has understood.
And also, you can read documents, but
you won't
get all the knowledge that the authors
put into the documents in the first
place. There's a lot of tacit knowledge
in projects. So, how do you deal with
that? And some of the Agile methods tend
to say
let's not document anything at all,
which actually isn't correct because
what most Agile methods suggest is that
you strip down documentation
to what's really necessary and what's
useful to document.
And
well, what I did is collect some best
practices, collect some patterns and
what kind of documentation is useful.
And
also, how to shape the documentation
that you think is necessary in your
project. So,
the book that you mentioned really
consists of two
distinct ideas. One is to strip down
documentation to a reasonable size
and the other is to
do the documentation that you decide is
necessary in such a way that it's really
useful,
that is well readable, comprehensible,
and generally worth doing and worth
reading.
So,
do you
I mean, so there are maybe two ways of
documenting things you could say. How,
you know, we we document
many things, but that we document those
only in a sketchy form. Um the opposite
approach could be to say, "Ah, let's
document less stuff, but make sure this
documentation is actually really nicely
done and accurate." Um any preferences
there?
Certainly uh the the second um
variation.
I mean, you could try and uh do lots of
documentation, but don't care very lot.
But then it would end up probably as as
right-only documents. Well, people take
take some time, though not very much,
doing the documentation, but no one's
going to read it anyway. Uh
so, there's really no point doing this.
Um what I'd recommend is that you
thoroughly go through a portfolio
of possible documents and decide in your
individual project which of these
documents are really necessary. And you
must really take into account that there
are things that are better discussed
among the team. And then, by the time
that someone will read the
documentation, they're probably already
outdated. So, it's not worth documenting
them. But if you have decided there's a
document you really want, because if you
don't do it, people
in the follow-up project or in a later
project stage will be in real trouble if
they don't have the document. If you
decide there's a purpose to a certain
document, then I suggest that you do it
well.
So, what constitutes good documentation?
And what is relevant? What is what is
worth being documented? I mean, there is
one thing that is probably relatively
obvious, and that is user manuals. Uh
so, if you have people that should be
able to use your system without you
sitting next to them, you have to
document a couple of things. But um I I
I kind of feel that's not the main
discussion point. So, because it's
rather obvious if you need it or not.
It's usually a deliverable. So, how do
you determine what to document?
Well, that depends on the individual
project and there's no way you can say
that
in a very
concrete way because it's really
different from one case to the other.
Well, user manuals are necessary because
users and the developers
almost all cases different groups of
people. So, that is the first criterion.
If there's information that you want to
make available to other people, people
outside the development team, well,
that's something that's worth
documenting because
the knowledge in the team is not
necessarily available to them.
Um
More generally, you must know who your
target audience is. So, in in the case
of
user manuals, the the target audience is
your users.
Um us other possible target audiences
could be other project teams. So,
neighboring project who do related
project where that ties into to your
software, the software that you're
building.
Um or maybe
a future team
who will work on the the next version of
your project, of your product. Um
Also, if you have a
teams that are disposed among several
places and you can't address all these
people in person, then you need to
distribute some amount of documentation.
Um
Long-term relevance is important. So,
lots of information expires rather
quickly.
Um but some information is likely to be
stable over
a reasonable period of time. Um
Design details often change rather
quickly, but the design principles, the
big picture, and also of design
rationale will probably be valuable
information even in the one to years.
And that's information that's worth
maintaining, worth keeping, and worth
making available to to future teams and
to to colleagues and others.
Maybe one thing I'd like to add I I
recently had a customer who was
hiring me actually specifically to find
out how to document their architecture.
And that was a tough question because
they started by writing maybe I think
100 pages of documents that that
explained architectural concepts and and
you know interface specification stuff
and they found out nobody read this
stuff. So it was basically useful or
useless, sorry. So one way of
documenting architectures at least in
that case that would have been more
successful and which they're hopefully
doing now
is to write tutorials and walkthroughs
because the audience for which this
document was intended wasn't, you know,
some high-level technical manager in
front of whom you want to justify your
architectural decisions. Rather you
wanted to communicate to your developers
how to
implement systems based on the
architecture. And and that is not
something you can describe by a kind of
reference document rather you need
something that takes a developer on
their hand by their hand and, you know,
walks through a typical application
development scenario. So I guess that's
that comes back to this target audience
thing. You need to make sure that you
not not just that the stuff you write
but also the way you write it and the
also, you know, it comes down to writing
style. Do you talk in the first person?
Do you talk in passive?
Comes down to whom you want to talk to
in the end.
I I agree with that and and
when I said you need to be aware for the
target audience is the first thing to
make sure is that there is a target
audience. You don't write documentation
no one's going to read at all. But the
second uh point to this is of course,
that's what you said, um that you must
adapt your documentation to your
specific audience and in terms of the
vocabulary that you use, um that the
technical terms, um
often it's wise to use quite realistic
examples. So, that the the people who
are expected to read the documentation
are able to understand it.
I think another important thing we
should discuss is when do you create
documentation? Do you do it at the end
of the project when everything's
finished? Do you do it as you go?
Java doc, for example, is something that
you typically do as you go because you
it's part of the API definition. So, do
you have any ideas on on when the right
time has come to to write which kind of
documents?
It really depends on the on the type of
document. There are things that you need
to document in advance.
Um
one
uh important thing is here
um that um sometimes you learn something
from documenting yourself. Sometimes you
gain insight. You commit something to
paper and you figure out you haven't
understood it really. Uh that's often
the case with specifications.
That's often the case with uh migration
concepts. Um
very often this is true with uh
um
things that you need to clarify together
with your customer
because when you you try to
write it down and you find out you
haven't understood it properly. So, you
go back
uh or perhaps ask the the customer to do
a review and then you'll find out what
misunderstandings
exist.
Um
because this will help you in later
project stages. It's important to to do
it up front.
Um this doesn't mean that you would have
to to document uh a specification for
instance to the to the finest detail
because you don't have to.
In many cases it's fine to document only
so far so that you can get started.
That's perfectly fine with me. But if
you think you you want to commit some of
the
requirements specification to paper, I
should do that up front.
And other things
uh for instance
uh a design document, I think that's
perfectly fine to do it once the the
design has been completed because if you
if you try and
uh document all the design decisions
immediately, you keep on documenting
your stuff more or less permanently and
it uses up so much time and eventually
people get bored and lose interest in in
permanent updates and the documentation
is likely to end up uh as documentation
that's at least not up to date. Perhaps
it's just downright inaccurate or false.
So
um it it really depends. If if you learn
something for the next project stage, uh
you should do it in advance. But if you
document something for later project
stages, uh then you you can uh
postpone the documentation until the
design has been completed
or the architecture has been completed
or even the system is up and running.
Uh do you think uh it's developer's job
to document or do you think um you
should have technical writers, technical
authors for doing the documentation or
should they at least do the review?
Uh any ideas there?
I guess in general it should be the the
the developers or the designers who
should document their own work. I mean
it's it's it's just extremely difficult
to to document someone else's thoughts.
Maybe it's impossible. I don't know, but
it's generally I think it's very
difficult.
On the other hand, that requires that
Joe developer or James architect
is actually able to produce decent
documents. So, they should be able to,
you know, come up with a good flow of
stuff and maybe even with a good looking
looking documentation. We will talk
about layout and stuff later, but
a similar question, how many of the
developers you know are actually good at
writing these kinds of things? It's a
provocative question, I guess, but um
Well, actually I think there's more than
you would think.
Um in almost all projects I've done,
there were people interested in doing
the documentation. I will admit that
there are projects where
there's no one really willing to do it,
but I think it's it's not the standard
situation.
A comment I'd like to give there before
we move on with with our original
plan is what I did a long time ago, that
was when I still was still employed by
by a consulting company, I tried to
write down a couple of guidelines of how
my colleagues should do documentation.
And and one thing I did was I basically
took the pattern form
and said, "Hey, whenever you document
something, always start with a context,
then describe the problem you wanted to
solve, then describe solution, describe
consequences, and then come up with an
example." And maybe with a set of
additional problems that result as a
consequence of your
solving the problem. So, maybe if you
don't really know how to structure a
document, if you explain something,
maybe take a look at the at the patterns
community style of how they try to
describe common and possibly complex
problems and take that as an inspiration
for structuring your own
documents. I've found that really very
helpful.
Yeah, I can imagine that
because
often you have you have of templates for
for documents and you can go further
than just providing
standard structure for certain
documents. You can even provide a
standard table of contents so that this
can serve as some kind of guideline to
to the developers. So they know that
they are missing certain areas they
should address. And it will just help
them
to to provide
the necessary documentation. And on the
other hand, what I said at the beginning
is it's it's not necessary to come up
with extremely voluminous documents.
Actually, that's a bad thing. Let's keep
in mind that
what we what I'm recommending it and and
what what the Agile method suggests is
that you strip down documentation to
what's really necessary. And I think
this is the a big pro for the developers
who aren't interested in doing
documentation stuff for weeks and weeks
and weeks because it's not necessary.
There's no benefit to that. So
the important thing is just to to
maintain the core ideas and that the
most important concepts and design ideas
so that they are not lost once the team
dissolves. And
this requires a certain amount of
documentation. That's right. But I think
um
well, my experience with releases is
relatively positive. Well, maybe I'm
biased because I'm a guy who who's
willing to do a certain amount of
documentation. But personally, I
wouldn't like to do documentation
exclusively. I do want to do designs. I
do want to do some programming, but the
occasional documentation is fine with
me. My experience is
several people feel similarly about
this.
I have to agree. I I really like to
nicely document something that is nice.
If you have a nice design or a nice
architecture, writing a nice
documentation walkthroughs is actually
fun sometimes. So, let's talk a little
bit about the structure of good
documentation.
Um we already mentioned this pattern
form thing, but that's not all.
Um so, do you have any recommendations
of how to successfully structure
uh documentation so that it's actually
nicely readable by by the potential
audience?
Well, I think there's some some very
simple techniques that can help you a
lot and they're very simple easy to
implement and they don't cost you a lot
of time or effort.
One is I think that each document should
be preceded by by some guidelines to the
readers just as an example because it
will help
um people identify which documents that
they they should read,
uh what's what are good things to know,
and what is completely irrelevant to
them and their jobs. Some other thing is
you could use some some sort of
structure tags that are similar maybe to
the pattern form, but it could be any
other sort of structure tags especially
when there's some uh repetitive or
systematic information. Also, you could
use tables for instance.
Um many IT people
tend to think in terms of categories
and so the table with its rows and
columns is sort of natural to to many IT
people and it expresses things in a very
clear way and it's very easily done. And
diagrams, of course, can be very useful.
Um
the drawback here, the flip side is that
diagrams are expensive to produce. If
you want to do a good diagram, it takes
time. There's no way around this.
Uh on the other hand,
uh pictures sometimes worth more than a
thousand words.
We all know this. So, um
for for design or for an architecture,
um
it does cost you some time, but it
probably
adds to the quality of the document. If
you really want to convey design idea or
the big picture of an architecture, and
that's something that's probably worth
documenting, the diagram can be
extremely useful.
I think it's important to point out that
diagrams alone usually don't work. Um
when we wrote um the remoting patterns
book where we essentially described the
architecture of remoting
infrastructures, we um always had a set
of sequence diagrams at the end of each
chapter that showed how the various
described components get together and in
in in the interaction wise. And the
feedback we got from all our reviewers
was, "Hey, those sequence diagrams are
great,
but please explain in prose text what
they contain."
And I thought, "Huh? You know, can't you
read a sequence diagram?" But the point
is, and I noticed that um myself, often
if you look at the diagram, you kind of
stare and you stare and you stare and
you stare and you stare and you see
something, but you you need maybe often
something that kind of guides you
through the diagram or points you to the
hot spots where to look and where to
actually focus your attention to. So, um
diagrams are are good as an additional
piece of information, but I think they
shouldn't be used as an exclusive one.
The worst case thing is that you say,
"You know, we have this documentation,
it's big Rose model. You can browse the
Rose file with Rose." I don't think
that's usually appropriate.
I agree completely. Yes. Um
diagrams are helpful, but but they don't
go as a replacement for for for your
text. And I guess your your readers were
certainly able to to read a sequence
diagram, but then the other question is
why is the sequence diagram the way it
is? So, what I mentioned earlier was the
design rationale. And why did you come
up with this design? What were the
design alternatives and why didn't you
pick other options? This is information
that is probably very useful
a couple of years later when when
there's going to be a revision of your
software, new version, or whatever. So,
this is information that's that's
probably useful, but it it doesn't come
out of the diagram. So, you need to
explain these things and language is
a much more powerful concept to to
explain these things than than a mere
diagram without information can ever be.
Maybe another comment on that, although
I maybe shouldn't talk that much.
If you want to describe a system or an
architecture systematically, it's also
very important that you yourself when
writing it agree on a limited set of
terms and language. So, you have to make
sure that you use consistent language
and a glossary can maybe help there. So,
you first define a number of terms. If
you do that in the extreme case, you can
even draw a meta model too. Just to
refer you back to the model-driven
development kind of thing. But, being
consistent in the
terms you use and in the way you
describe things is very important
because otherwise you'll
just confuse the reader. But, let's
let's go on in in in our whatever we
tried to plan here.
So,
I'd like to elaborate a little bit on
the question of
documentation that you basically read on
the train or on the toilet or wherever
versus documentation that you use to
look up stuff. JavaDoc being the
prime prime example.
What of the things which of the things
you discussed already are applicable for
which of those different kinds? Do you
think there is important differences? Is
one more important than the other or
any opinions there?
I think there are basically
two different ways to
well, read any
to to access written material. One way
is to read it and the other is to browse
it. Those two
uh two really different ways. And and
reading is what you do with with the
things that are printed on paper. And
browsing is what you do when you look up
information. And ideally, this is
information that's available
electronically,
um maybe on a web, on a wiki, on an
internet, whatever.
And I think if you if you have a a fully
fledged concept, a design concept, or an
architecture description, this probably
qualifies for for a document that it can
be read. So, most people want to to go
through this, go go backwards and
forwards, make annotations to it, and
maybe to take home. So, um
it should it should be available in the
form that allows printing. And that's
not an HTML page in most cases. On the
other hand, things like API
specifications
um
are just This is just a cool example of
what must be available online. I mean,
what what when do you look up things in
in your in your
specification? When do you use Java Doc?
Normally, while you're programming,
while you're coding. So, you you just
look things up, and it must be readily
available.
Um of course, there are overlaps.
There's no doubt that
some documents need to be available both
for print
and online.
And um
this is something you can't avoid, and
you need some to do something about it.
Which brings us to the discussion about
technology and techniques. So, should I
write my documentation in Word, or do I
generate stuff from diagrams, or from
rows, or from Java? So, do you have any
best practice I know it's probably a
complicated topic, but do you have any
best practices suggestions there?
Well,
I guess the thing to understand is that
you can generate views,
but you cannot generate content. So, um
in many cases, when you say you have
some kind of document that you want to
make available in one medium, well, like
for for printing it, like you just just
have to write it. You cannot generate
it. What you can try to generate is uh
as I said, there are overlaps. If you
want one document available both with
HTML and for the web. Um this is an
option for for generating uh
one of these views, probably the the the
web view. And and also one prominent
example of uh of uh
documentation generation is of course
Javadoc. Everybody knows this. And it's
very useful, so so you have the
documentation
of the code directly uh next to the
code, but you also have
a perfect API specification that you
could generate and you can browse
through.
Um
So, you you can apply techniques uh to
generate different views of the same
information, but I'm afraid that the the
usefulness of of documentation
generation is is generally rather
limited.
Next thing I would like to talk about is
actually some of the
uh layout and and and visual properties
of nicely done documentation. And um to
to go a little bit into history, um the
first
thing I personally saw from all this uh
documentation work that Andreas was
working on was actually a pattern
language that talked about how to nicely
format documents. And his own papers
that he submits to the EuroPlaP and
other conferences is is written using
that style, and we'll put a couple of
samples in the show notes. And I really
really like that stuff. So, I think
that's my opinion, or I would claim, um
if things are nicely formatted, then
it's easier for people to actually read
this stuff. I really hate it if I have
these, you know, documents where there's
a line spacing probably less than the
font height and extremely long lines.
So, I really think you should elaborate
a little bit on the best practices that
um
that you came up with with regards to
how to nicely format documents.
Yes. I mean, uh admittedly, this is
nothing to do with Agile specifically.
This is really
um characteristics of of good
uh documentation documentation that's
well done. There are some general rules
on layout and typography. Actually,
typography is an art in its in its own
right. And there's there's uh lots of
things you could possibly do.
Um but there are also some very simple
rules that can easily be obeyed and that
uh will help you design documents that
look much better
much more readable. Uh one is the the
one rule, for instance, is that you
shouldn't overuse different fonts. I
mean,
uh sometimes uh
documents use like four or five or six
different fonts and that's just very
difficult to read. Also,
um it's a good idea to use a serif font
for as for as as the main font, not
necessarily for the headings, but for
for the main text because it's just uh
better readable and there's evidence for
that because people have been doing
experiments over
over 50 years now what what kind of uh
typography uh helps readers uh read a
paper. And
one extreme example is is for instance
the the use of of all capitals. So, some
people do that to to point out uh
passages in the text that are supposedly
uh very important. But but if you use
all caps, that's completely unreadable
and reading takes people up to 20 or 30%
more time. And the effect is that people
won't read it at all. Um there are other
things like like you don't
put too much text on one page but but
leave a reasonable margin etc. etc. And
there is some some very simple rules.
Now I just put those into pattern form
and put them into the book. And
though it's not exactly
it has nothing to do really with with
Agile. It's just the characteristics of
good documentation general but but
people seem to like it and the funny
thing is when I give seminars on on
documentation, this is something that
people are often really interested in.
And also it comes really cheap. So
as I say as I mentioned earlier,
normally you have some some templates in
your organization for for doing
documentation. Not everybody is supposed
to come up with their own documentation
templates. So what you can do is design
your templates to meet at least
the most important and most basic
typographic rules. And that will do a
lot of good and it's it's really easy
easily done. It's it's simple and
straightforward but
So two two more of those rules that you
are patterns that you came up with had
to do with line length and line spacing
and I find these to be maybe the most
important. I think you really should
mention those.
Well if you if you have a line that's
really short, that's
that's maybe okay. This is what you have
in newspapers
but you have to go from one line to the
next relatively often. And you should
have reasonably
length lines and and for papers in in a
normal environment where you read at
home or at your desk. But if if your
lines are too long,
that becomes easily unreadable because
people will confuse the the lines. This
is something that that happens
unconsciously but but you
you can measure the effect and the the
general rule is to have about two lower
case alphabets
uh, on on one line. So, line should be
uh, should allow for two lower-case
alphabets.
As as a spacing, um, the the general
rule is that you the the spacing should
be 120% of the font size. So, if you
have a 10 uh, point font, then you need
12 point for for each uh, line. This is
something that most word processing
systems do correctly anyway, but it's
worth checking.
Yeah, and as I said, since these are
visual properties of documents we're
talking about, uh, I'll put a couple of
samples, maybe with some of the original
pattern papers, uh, let's see, maybe
into the show notes.
How do you do quality assurance for
documents? I mean,
ideally you want to write automated unit
tests for documents probably, but that's
that's not that easy. So,
uh, so probably it's about reviews or or
or proofreading. So, any suggestions how
to how to implement that in practice?
Well, yeah, I I think there's this uh,
saying that that uh, documents need
reviews like code needs testing.
Um, well, reviews are a useful technique
obviously. Um, you shouldn't do too much
of that. So, you you need not review or
have every document reviewed. Uh, but at
some stage reviews become necessary.
This is true especially if you if you
hand out the documents to your
customers. So, it I think it's important
that someone has looked at a document
before you you give it to the customer.
Um,
sometimes uh,
the the review can be done by the
customers themselves, which is extremely
useful because you you can integrate
your customers.
Um, you they get the impression that you
take them seriously, which is important.
And you you probably learn a lot because
the experience shows that uh, well,
development team and the customer
often don't speak the same language and
misunderstandings happen easily. So, um
obviously you'll have meetings. This is
what what the Agile methods say.
Ideally customers are on site and you
work on the customer's site. But,
this is to make sure that in in the the
communication between you and the
customer,
you
there's a straightforward
communication and you can rule out
misunderstandings as as quickly as
possible. And the same's true for
documents. So,
have them reviewed. Um customer reviews
are very useful technique.
Obviously you can ask other people on
the team to to review the designs that
you have documented because that will
allow you to to get easy feedback, early
feedback on what you've done. Although
probably the design review
a design document normally captures what
has been discussed in the design
meeting. So,
this should probably summarize something
to which several people have
contributed. But, anyway,
review is
is important for all documents
that have reached the stage of
somewhat final stage or at least you
want to make them the document available
to a large number of people. So, you
need to make sure that you don't confuse
them by
by making inaccurate information
available just to telling things that
will rather confuse them than help them.
Now, we talked a whole lot about
written documentation. Actually, the
whole episode is about written
documentation. Do you think it's
worthwhile to also explore other forms
of documentation and when? For example,
you could, instead of documenting a
design as a document, you could have two
team members
standing on the flip chart explaining
the design to each other and video
taping that. So, that new team members
can watch this on video instead of
reading stuff. Do you have any
experiences or opinions on the
suitability of these kinds of
approaches?
I think it's worth trying out. I think
it really depends on the individual
situation on the individual project. I
mean, there's various things you can do.
Video taping is one thing. The other
thing is once relatively easily done is
at the end of the design discussion you
can take your digital camera and just
make a copies of of what's been written
on the whiteboard.
It's useful to some extent, I believe.
It probably captures
only
as far as the the the camera is
concerned just captures the outcome of
of the design.
And if it's readable if if if it's if if
if the quality of the photos is okay,
then you can probably use it in in a
design document and that's okay.
As as for video types,
it's it's a cool idea and I like it.
I suspect that in many cases it's not
that easily accessible because people
just can't flip
forth and back through the pages what
they could do with a written document.
On the other hand, if if it's easily
done and it captures a really
interesting discussion,
it's something I would encourage you to
try out.
Maybe another thing would be in the next
project that I actually a good idea. The
next project I'm going to be I'll do the
weekly project podcast and in the worst
case project budget must buy everybody
an iPod or some MP3 player. Now,
honestly, I mean, usually in many
projects people have to commute quite a
bit to get to the workplace. Why not
every couple of days capture a
discussion between I don't know the
architect and the manager and the
developer and and and try to to to come
up with information about what people
need to know.
Why not?
Come to think of it, it sounds like a
good idea. I think a video type or
even an MP3 file that captures
discussions is probably more useful than
than a mere photograph.
Yeah. So, that's something I'll try it
on my next project. So, um to to wrap
this discussion up, I think we should
close with going back to some of the
more
related stuff. I mean, both of us and
maybe most of you listeners are probably
involved in projects that would probably
call themselves more or less agile. So,
the question is how do you integrate the
task of documenting and reviewing and
all that stuff into an HR project. So, I
think we should
discuss a little bit on on this topic.
Well, what I said in the beginning was
that it's important to to strip down
documentation to to what's really
necessary.
There's no such rule as the more you
document
the more you benefit. It's not a linear
thing.
And you should really
take care not to document too much but
would really be skeptical about the the
usefulness of documentation.
Um and I think on the other hand, you
should be aware that that certain amount
of documentation is necessary and you
should integrate this into into a
project plan. So, you should assign it a
budget ultimately. You you should
define specify a work package that
includes the documentation. It should
come with responsibility. So, who's in
charge? Not just Not Not everybody. Not
nobody. Just one person.
Um There should be a deadline. Um So, it
should be part of the planning.
Speaking of Agile, um, I think this is
some kind of summary.
Uh, I think it's important to understand
that that documentation and verbal
communication aren't aren't opposed to
each other. And Agile methods stress the
importance of for for
verbal communication, and I'll second
that.
Uh, and and they also uh,
suggest that uh, a smaller amount of
written documentation
uh, is probably a good idea. And I
wholeheartedly agree.
And I think that uh, that
written documentation and and verbal
communication really uh, complement each
other. Not uh,
not not not alternatives, but they
really really complement each other.
And
Agile is an attitude
uh, more than a set of techniques. Agile
is uh, an attitude that is probably best
described by a
and and do the right thing. Do the
things that are really important. Think
about what really matters and do that.
And if you apply that
uh,
attitude documentation, you probably end
up with with documents that are useful.
Maybe not very many, but with a set of
of documents that are useful and and
will help you your project in the later
stages or even future projects.
Is it too far of a stretch if I'd say
that you can even maybe apply more of
the Agile practices? Like for example,
you could have customer on site means
customer reviews documents. You could do
pair writing. You do test driven
development in the sense that I mean
it's probably a stretch, but um, in the
sense that you first decide what the
goals are of what you want to document.
You define the audience. You define what
you want to achieve, and then you write
the documentation. And there are
probably more Agile techniques that
could be paraphrased for for
documentation.
I guess you can, yeah. Um Agile is a set
of techniques, but as I said, it's
mostly an attitude, but but yeah, it's
it's a it's a set of techniques, but
these techniques are not not techniques
in in the sense of software development,
but techniques in how to
to deal with each other in the project,
how to to manage your your work and your
work load, how to to collaborate on the
team. And these techniques apply to
documentation all the same. That's
right.
Okay, so I guess this wraps up that
episode. Um
thank you for listening and thanks
Andreas for being on the show.
Thank you for inviting me.
Thanks for listening to Software
Engineering Radio. If you want to get
more information about Software
Engineering Radio, or if you want to
give us feedback, please go to our
website at SE-Radio.net.
You can also contact the team at
team@se-radio.net.
Although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think. Software
Engineering Radio wants to thank Henning
Pauli for the intro and outro music, as
well as Loop Send for providing the
bandwidth.
This episode of SE Radio, as well as all
other episodes, is licensed under
Creative Commons License. See the
Software Engineering Radio website for
details.